<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="tawc_buffer_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright 2026 tawc contributors
    SPDX-License-Identifier: MIT
  </copyright>

  <description summary="AHardwareBuffer sharing for Android Wayland compositor">
    This protocol allows Wayland clients to share GPU buffers with the
    compositor using Android's AHardwareBuffer mechanism. Buffer data is
    transferred over a side-channel Unix socket (because AHB serialization
    uses multiple fds that don't fit Wayland's single-fd-per-argument model),
    while buffer lifecycle is coordinated via this protocol.
  </description>

  <interface name="tawc_buffer_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="factory for AHB buffer channels">
      The global entry point for AHB buffer sharing. Clients bind this
      to create per-surface AHB channels.
    </description>

    <request name="get_channel">
      <description summary="create an AHB channel for a surface">
        Creates an AHB channel associated with a wl_surface. The compositor
        will send a channel_fd event on the returned object with a Unix
        socket fd for AHB transfer.

        Only one channel may be active per surface.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="tawc_ahb_channel_v1"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="tawc_ahb_channel_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="AHB transfer channel for a surface">
      Represents a side-channel connection for transferring AHardwareBuffers
      between client and compositor for a specific wl_surface.

      The client sends AHBs via AHardwareBuffer_sendHandleToUnixSocket on the
      side-channel socket, then calls attach to inform the compositor. The
      compositor receives the AHB and imports it as a GPU texture.

      The standard wl_surface.commit triggers presentation of the most
      recently attached AHB.
    </description>

    <event name="channel_fd">
      <description summary="side-channel socket for AHB transfer">
        Sent by the compositor immediately after channel creation. The fd
        is one end of a Unix socketpair. The client uses
        AHardwareBuffer_sendHandleToUnixSocket on this fd to transfer
        AHB handles to the compositor.
      </description>
      <arg name="fd" type="fd" summary="side-channel socket file descriptor"/>
    </event>

    <request name="attach">
      <description summary="attach an AHB that was sent on the side channel">
        Informs the compositor that an AHardwareBuffer has been sent on the
        side-channel socket. The compositor will receive it via
        AHardwareBuffer_recvHandleFromUnixSocket.

        The width and height describe the buffer dimensions. The compositor
        uses these for layout before the AHB is fully received.

        This request is double-buffered like wl_surface.attach: it sets the
        pending buffer, which is applied on the next wl_surface.commit.
      </description>
      <arg name="width" type="int" summary="buffer width in pixels"/>
      <arg name="height" type="int" summary="buffer height in pixels"/>
    </request>

    <event name="release">
      <description summary="compositor is done with the buffer">
        Sent when the compositor no longer needs the most recently committed
        AHB. After receiving this event, the client may reuse or destroy the
        AHardwareBuffer.
      </description>
    </event>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the channel">
        Destroys the AHB channel. Any pending or committed buffers may still
        be in use by the compositor until released.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
